Guide to the Selden Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Selden family papers
1787-1883
MS 673
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.83
4 boxes
Correspondence, writings (including school essays and exercises, poetry and political essays), miscellaneous accounts, school bills, and other papers of the Selden family of Hadlyme, Connecticut. The principal family members represented are Richard Ely Selden (1797-1868), a member of the class of 1818 at Yale, a justice of the peace, and a state senator, and his son Samuel Hart Selden (1826-1891), a member of the class of 1848.
Selden family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library in 1973.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Hart Selden was the second son of Richard Ely Selden (1797-1868), who graduated from Yale College in 1818, was a farmer and a member of the Connecticut State Senate in 1844. Samuel's mother was Elizabeth, daughter of William Lynde, of Saybrook, Connecticut. He was born in Hadlyme, in the township of Lyme, Connecticut, March 16, 1826.
After graduation from Yale College in 1848, it was his desire to study for the ministry, but his health did not permit. For a year he was a tutor in the family of William Denniston, in Salisbury Mills, New York, and thereafter followed the profession of civil engineering. From 1850 to 1862 he was engaged in railroad work, principally with the Erie & Pittsburgh Railroad, making his home at first in Batavia, New York, and afterwards in Erie and Girard, Pennsylvania. From 1862 to the time of his death he was connected with the Chicago & Northwestern Railway, as resident engineer in charge of the North Michigan Peninsula Division, residing for three years at Marquette, and from 1865 at Escanaba, Michigan.
On June 16, 1853, Selden married Sarah A., the eldest child of Oliver I. Lay, of Lyme, Connecticut. Mrs. Selden and five of their seven daughters outlived him. The third daughter is the wife of C. P. Coffin (Yale, 1881), and the fourth of T. H. Linsley (Yale, 1876s). Early in November 1891, Selden left Escanaba with his family for their winter home in Harrison, Florida. Making a few days' stop at Linsley's home in Evanston, Illinois, he was there taken ill with erysipelas and passed away on November 25, 1891, at the age of 65.
Selden was a man of winning presence, of strong character, and of deep religious convictions. For twenty-five years he was an elder in the Presbyterian Church. His life was blameless and his influence strongly felt in the community on the side of religion and morality.
(Derived from Yale Obituary Record, 1859-70 and 1880-1902).
Scope and Contents
Correspondence, writings (including school essays and exercises, poetry and political essays), miscellaneous accounts, school bills, and other papers of the Selden family of Hadlyme, Connecticut. The principal family members represented are Richard Ely Selden (1797-1868), a member of the class of 1818 at Yale, a justice of the peace, and a state senator, and his son Samuel Hart Selden (1826-1891), a member of the class of 1848.
Families; Connecticut -- Politics and government; Hadlyme (Conn.) -- History; United States -- Politics and government; Legislators; Politicians; Selden, R. E. (Richard Ely), 1797-1868; Selden, Samuel Hart, 1826-1891; Selden family; Yale College (1718-1887). Class of 1818; Yale University -- Students
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  The Selden Family Papers consists of correspondence, writings (including school essays and exercises, poetry, and political essays), and miscellaneous accounts, school bills, and other papers of the Selden family of Hadlyme, Connecticut. The papers relate principally however, to Richard Ely Selden, 1797-1868, who was a graduate of Yale University, class of 1818, a justice of the peace, and, in 1844, a member of the Connecticut state senate.
  The correspondence, 1795-1862, consists primarily of letters to Richard Ely Selden, a significant number being from fellow members of the class of 1818; there are also some letters form family members. Also included in the correspondence are drafts of letters that Selden wrote to others, some of these being letters to the editors of local newspapers regarding topics of political or religious interest.
  Among the writings are school essays and exercises, written by Richard Ely Selden and by his son, Samuel Hart Selden (Yale, 1848), with several "epic poems" by the former on political subjects.
  - Correspondence
    - 1795, 1815-1817 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1818-1819 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - 1832, 1835-1836, 1838-1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - 1840-1842, 1844-1848, 1850-1851, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Invitations sent to Richard E. Selden (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Writings: poetry (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Writings: essays and exercises (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - College bills and other Yale-related papers (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous legal papers (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Selden family-miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Additional Material, 1787-1883; Accession 2018-M-0031
  Arrangement
  The accession is arranged by type of material and therein chronologically.
  This accession comprises ledgers, farm recoeds, and family papers documenting the Selden family's farm life in Lyme, Connecticut. The ledgers, 1787-1884, were maintained by Richard Ely Selden and record purchases and payments for goods and services and logs of employee's activities and pay. Transactions include business dealings for timber, grass, hay, fish, livestock, and produce. The ledgers primarily document the farm's business, but they also record births and deaths, marriages performed by Selden, poems, and other personal matters. The farm records, 1787-1845, comprise manuscript material pertaining to the farm's business operations. The family papers, 1812-1868, comprise clippings, writings, and poetry pertaining to the Selden family.
  - Ledgers
    - 1787-1803 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - 1803-1807 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - 1807-1814 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - 1817-1833 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1824-1850 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - 1850-1877 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
    - 1850-1883 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Farm records
    - 1787-1845 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Family papers
    - 1812-1868 (Box 2, Folder 6)